github.com/amyxlu

amyxlu@cs.toronto.edu +1-647-968-6833 linkedin.com/in/amyxlu

Summary

I am a graduate student at the University of Toronto/Vector Institute for AI. I am interested in **developing** biologically-principled machine learning methods, with an emphasis on self-supervised representation learning, generalizability, and biological interpretability. I also serve on Research to the People, which organizes research collaborations of genomics/ML researchers for patients of understudied diseases.

EDUCATION

University of Waterloo

Bachelors of Science, Honours Science, Bioinformatics Option

University of Toronto, Vector Institute

Master's in Computer Science

Stanford University

Visiting Student, Departments of Computer Science and Genetics

Waterloo, Canada

2014 - 2019

Toronto, Canada

Jan 2019 - Present

Sept 2019 - Present

Experience

Stanford University

Palo Alto, USA

Visiting Student Researcher — Domain Adaptation in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Anshul Kundaje

2019 - Present

• Domain adaptation, ChIP-seq data, interpretability: Using domain adaptation methods to improve transcription factor binding prediction when evaluating in different cellular contexts.

University of Toronto/Vector Institute

Toronto, Canada

Masters Student — Representation learning in genomics, Dr. Alan Moses & Dr. Marzyeh Ghassemi 2019 – Present

- Self-supervised learning, natural language processing: Adapting attention-based NLP models to learn self-supervised representations of protein sequences.
- Generalizability, computer vision: Benchmarked self-supervised and canonical computer vision methods in a
 microscopy image dataset with covariate shift to highlight generalization failures in machine learning. (NeurIPS
 2019; ICML 2019 Self-Supervised Learning Workshop)
- Algorithmic fairness, clinical decision support: Quantitative and qualitative evaluation of bias in "black box" contextual word embeddings on clinical notes. Explored debiasing methods using adversarial gradient-reversal. (NeurIPS 2019 Workshop for ML for Healthcare, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML.)

Harvard Medical School/Boston Children's Hospital

Boston, USA

Research Intern — Machine Learning in Clinical Genomics, Dr. Piotr Sliz

2018 - 2019

- Genotype-phenotype studies, clinical interpretability: Understanding disease genotype-phenotype relationships using machine learning models. Interpreted important model features to seek novel disease-associated variants from whole exome (WES) data.
- Variant filtering, pathway analyses: Applied standard filtering pipelines for false-positive variants. Explored classification from pathway- and variant-level features.
- Machine learning, dimensionality reduction: Focused on capturing epistatic non-linearities and dimensionality reduction.

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

Undergraduate Thesis Student — Deep Learning in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Andrew Doxey

2017 - 2018

- Convolutional neural networks in genomics: Implemented a convolutional neural network which classifies ATAC-seq accessibile regions with 91% accuracy.
- Interpretability: Interpreted the neural network by reconstructing the first-layer feature map as position-weighted matrix (PWM) motif. All motifs found statistical matches in JASPAR, a database of known motifs.
- Phylogenetics, metagenomic data mining: Used various bioinformatics pipeline tools (HMMER, BLAST, etc.) to understand biochemical properties of potentially uncharacterized toxins in metagenomic data.
- Self-directed learning: Self-learned deep learning concepts and Python as a biology student.

École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Research Intern — Molecular Dynamics Simulations, Dr. Matteo Dal Parero

Lausanne, Switzerland 2017

- Molecular dynamics: Used molecular dynamics (MD) and GROMACS to simulate enzyme-membrane mechanisms of bacterial "superbugs".
- Workflow automation: Analyzed and automated simulations using R, tcl/tk, and Csh scripts.

University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

Research Intern — Data Visualization in Pharmacoepidemiology, Dr. Suzanne Cadarette

2015 - 2017

• Data visualization, pharmacoepidemiology: Used R to visualize the social diffusion of methodological innovation. Contributed to two co-authored publications and an international epidemiology conference.

AWARDS

- NSERC Michael Smith Foreign Supplement: Supports high-calibre Canadian graduate students in pursuing research abroad. Valued at \$6,000.
- Canada Graduate Scholarships-Master's (CGS-M) Award: NSERC federal research grant. Valued at \$17,500.
- Scholarship of Excellence in Research: One of 13 students sponsored for research at EPFL. Valued at CHF 4,500.
- University of Waterloo: Various entrance awards totaling \$6,000.
- Associate of The Royal Conservatory (ARCT): Performer's Diploma in Piano.

Publications and Conference Proceedings

- Published: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. The Cells Out of Sample (COOS) dataset and benchmarks for measuring out-of-sample generalization of image classifiers. *Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems* (NeurIPS) 2019.
- Submitted: Zhang H*, Lu AX*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. *Equal contribution.
- Presented: Moses A, Lu AX, Lu AXP, Ghassemi M. Transfer Learning vs. Batch Effects: what can we expect from neural networks in computational biology? *Machine Learning for Computational Biology (MLCB) 2019*.
- Published: Ban J, Tadrous M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Cadarette SM. Diffusion of indirect comparison meta-analytic methods to study drugs: a systematic review and co-authorship network analysis. *BMJ Open*.
- Under revision: Consiglio GP, Maclure M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Ban JK, McCarthy L, Cadarette SM. Guidance documents for the application of Self-controlled Crossover Observational PharmacoEpidemiology (SCOPE) designs are needed: systematic review and animated co-authorship networks. Submitted to Pharmacoepi Drug Saf.

Workshop Papers and Posters

- Presented: Lu AX*, Zhang H*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Poster presentation, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health. *Equal contribution.
- Presented: Zhang H*, Lu AX*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Extended Abstract, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Machine Learning for Healthcare. *Equal contribution.
- Presented: Abdalla M, Zhang H, Lu AX, Chen I, Ghassemi M. Quantifying Fairness in a Multi-Group Setting and its Impact in the Clinical Setting. Poster presentation, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health.
- Presented: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. Paired Cell Inpainting: A Multiple-Instance Extension of Self-Supervised Learning for Bioimage Analysis. *Poster presentation*, *ICML 2019 Workshop on Self-Supervised Learning*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Rockowitz S, Poduri A, Sliz P. From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. *Poster. Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019.*
- Submitted: Lu AX, Tam ES. Effect of prophylactic brimonidine on subconjunctival hemorrhage in laser-assisted cataract surgery. *Poster abstract*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Consiglio GP, Cadarette SM. Dynamic Visualization in Co-Authorship Network Analysis. Poster presentation. Leslie Dan Faculty of Pharmacy Undergraduate Research Symposium.
- Presented: McIlroy-Young R, Lu AX, Guenther N, Olarnyk A. A Network Analysis: Did the Arab Spring Impact the Academic Network of Tunisia Between 2010 and 2015? Poster presentation. Knowledge Integration Symposium.

SERVICE AND ACTIVITIES

- Research to the People (formerly SVAI): Core Team of Research to the People, a non-profit connecting patients of rare genomic diseases to the medical/AI research community and industry partners through collaborative research initiatives.
- Residence Don: Organized events and established rapport with diverse students. Responded to mental health and conduct crises. Leader for the Velocity Residence, a spin-off for the Velocity start-up incubator.
- Tosamaganga Hospital, Tanzania: Supported operations at a rural Tanzanian hospital and shadowed surgical procedures. Expenses were covered by scholarships, fundraising, and part-time tutoring.

Teaching

- Teaching Assistant, Genetics: Taught tutorials for BIOL 239 at the University of Waterloo.
- Piano, music theory: Taught piano performance (up to RCM 7), ear training, RCM music history, and RCM Intermediate Rudiments.
- Tutoring: Tutor for IB Math and IB Chemistry.

Talks

- Vector NLP Talks: Quantifying and Removing Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Co-presenter.
- Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019: From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. *Lightning talk*.

SELECTED HACKATHON PROJECTS

- Chatsense: Mobile chat app using a sentiment analysis machine learning API on voice messages and mapping dominant emotions to emojis, designed for the autistic community. Team project. "Can a Computer Hear How You Feel?" prize: YHacks at Yale.
- Alice: Web login page using a trained facial recognition model to login to online banking without passwords, designed for dementia patients. *Team project. Desjardin prize: ConUHacks III.*